Okay so now we're going to start this portrait of Lisa. Okay so first
I'm going to start with these proportions. So look at the proportions of the head
starting with the plumb line. Okay then we'll look for the unit of measurement
which is the brow. Take that across there. Then if we double up this unit of measurement
that comes to just below the chin. Then check this measurement to here it's the next third.
So proportionally the head is three and a third normally so we've got some extra hair there.
So the extra the hair is about the is the third.
What means chins are usually slightly shorter than a man's chin. Okay so then we're going to use
these units of measurement around the face first. Let's look for this unit of measurement here.
Okay so I'm going to give us the the socket and then I'm going to look for this third.
So just below the chin to the brow that comes about there.
Then if I take all three thirds in the plumb line that comes to about here.
Then if I look for the the halfway point of the underside of the eye
to double that line up that's about halfway. Then if I take this
measurement it goes just beyond the frame so about half that measurement if I double that up.
So half that measurement comes about there. Just check that again maybe a bit less
somewhere around there. Try that again. Okay so then if we look at the brow
that's about half of that half measurements it's like a quarter measurement of the nose to brow.
So as the eye turns away we're seeing a lot less
of the eye as we turn away as it turns away. Then if we look at the top of the head
check that measurement that comes about there. Okay so that's about a third third of a nose to
brow. Okay so if we look at the so first we'll start with the placement on the head
of the head on the canvas. First of all going to load up my brush shape the brush
wipe some of the paint off by brushing technique. So I'm going to go to mark the top of the head.
Okay so then going to mark with that third would come.
Okay so giving allowance for that and then I'm thinking
where that third is going to come underneath the chin. So I'm going to make the head around eight
inches so it's the top so it's the bottom of the chin so that comes around there.
One at the bottom the third so I'm thinking that's the third that'll be the chin so that extra third
so it comes around there
which is the bottom of the chin. Actually I'm going to give it a bit extra just so it's easier
the head is a bit bigger that's about here so the third will come to about there
just so it's easier to um the video so I'm making this bigger but an inch bigger
so around I'm making this about nine nine inches no I'm not okay it's about there eight and a half
so what's that that's about three centimeters bigger or two
so that third comes around there okay so
so I'm going to divide these thirds up so I'm looking for a third something like that
so kind of ignoring that where that chin would be ignoring that head up the head
just looking for these thirds at the minute I'm going to go that about there
right there and that's that right there okay so then from there
I'm going to guess where that chin is okay and as before guess where the top of the head is
I'm going to say something around there okay so this is the bottom of the chin
so I'm just going to look for the um the width okay I'll just indicate that
so we know where the brown is okay so a chin to the top of the head
width that's about the same so a chin to the top of the head
so I just want to make sure that the head's going to fit on the paper
if I put the back of the head around here run to the head about there okay
so then the um distance between the the the profile of the head it's a plumb line
and so that's around a quarter so if I
look for my halfway point so around there then take a look for this quarter
it's somewhere there so that a quarter way in that's where the plumb line's going to be
so I'll call it there okay I'm going to load up the brush now
so put this plumb line in wipe the brush off back to try and brush in so now we can look at these
look for these um so I was a bit far over there just going to reinstate these measurements
on the plumb line okay so this is my round line bottom of the nose
right so now going to look for so we're going to break up I'm going to look for some of these
proportions so first proportion and socket remember which side of the line you're measuring from
okay then halfway so on the side of the eye then if we took this third this measurement
underneath the chin that's going to hit the shiny part of the ear
then go from this third out that's about the hairline
okay so the hairline then come in leads about there but anyway let's just put that marking
start off with okay so we've got these basic units of measurements okay
then say if we've got the um this line of the chin
look at that line of chin to where the the lip hits the plumb line that's about halfway
so looking for this measurement do all that measurement up okay so that's about halfway
that's where the lip hits the plumb line um okay so as there are basic units of measurements
now we can start to look for the outline I'll do that with blue okay so the first thing
you can look for is this angle of the brow just right on the um that line of the um
the brow line okay then
if we think about the actual underside of the brow there is a change of angle just underneath that
then if I use my brush okay looking at that angle just bring that angle over okay then
if look at the um where the underside of the lid comes that's just below the halfway point
somewhere around there then if look where the cheek comes just to the inside of that brow
somewhere around there so this is going to be the outside edge that'll be the outside edge there
just to bear that in mind okay that needs to come in a bit further so that's the outside edge
okay then it's a change of angle it's more or less on the line of the nose
and that kind of hits so from the underside of the nose here just underneath
the shadow of the lip we have this angle then look at the bottom of the chin so we've got this
angle here just more or less straight so where does that start angle there angle there then
this angle coming up to the lip okay so it probably starts it kind of starts from here
comes down to the think about the bottom of the chin that comes across a slight angle there
okay then where does the neck come so the neck is about a halfway mark halfway so it comes in halfway
from the plumb line okay this is from the chin to the shoulder that's just a bit longer
but a halfway so halfway about there a bit longer that's that change of angle so then
we can look at the shoulder so I'm going to look for this so I'm just going to eyeball this change of
angle straightens off and the change of angle so I'm going to take that angle using my brush
transfer that over then it straightens off around here then you've got this little
change of angle there and another one another one there okay so I'm going to look at the
forehead okay so this line here okay I'll call it there so that's about a halfway
between the brow top of the head okay so you've got that little indication of the head
it starts coming from the from the plumb line okay so then from there it comes to one side
if we think about all this this is going to be the outside edge base okay just bear that in mind
okay then we've got a bit of hair here just the one side of the plumb line
then there's the the so I've just put that line in there this bit of hair
so now I'm looking for the apex of the head which is more less in line
with the eye socket indicate that so now I've looked at it for this change of angle here
that's just above that third so I've got a third there something to that angle
just above that third something like that like a change of angle the hair okay now we can
look at the back of the head okay so I'm just going to check the back of the head again
so to the hairline so yeah that's a bit short of a third so this is my third to a third
so it comes about there okay so now let's look for this measurement most obvious measurement is this
measurement here so where's that in relation to the lip in relation to that third
so just underneath the lip along there just in from that ear shade there okay now we can
transfer these lines over the angles taking that angle this angle okay now we can look for
this angle it's quite an obvious angle here okay so where's that in relation to
that third in the ear third measured so just on the inside of the third of the ear just over
that third that we measured okay we can look for these angles then where about is this apex
of the hair so the apex of the hair the back that's just below the apex of the hair the back
just below the eye somewhere around there okay so I've got that so I'm going to look for those
angles using my brush it comes in there okay it comes down there all right then where's the
next change of angle so that's going to be in line with the brow okay so in line with the brow
look at that angle transfer that over okay how deep is that hairline and put in a
um baseline okay from those two points to measure the depth of that shape so got the baseline
measuring the depth that's terms that I'm going to come to about here okay so that's going to be
it's about there depth that eye there's something around that okay almost for the same angle so I'm
just going to copy that angle so then so from the apex here hair curves call that the middle
so the hair curves curves again I see it turns in look for these changes of angle here start off
with slight change of angle there here comes up change of angle there that's your rough
rough guideline okay articulation there so looking back at the hair looking for that
change of angle just going to guess that slight step around here that's roughly the outside
okay go back curl so that curl just starts just underneath this change of angle
thumbs up there something like that okay now we can start to look for the inside outline
but this might fit here so I'm just going up this apex of the ear we're about to start
and just goes a bit beyond that point then look at that in relation to the eye
around there apex top and bottom of the ear let's look for that bottom of the ear
sitting line with the nose bottom of the ear okay top of the ear just underneath
the um the brow something around there so the darker side of the edge
the darker side of the line represents the darker edge okay so now I'm looking for
so something around this tragus there's any measurements
bit around there it's about to take that tragus shape okay that's just a bit short of the chin
so just something around there to there tragus that should be somewhere around there
and look for the um what's something for the lip to brow or I'll put something for this chin to
brow okay chin to brow let's look at that chin to brow the that should hit hopefully will be the
head of the neck okay okay it's the tragus I'm just going to measure that one more time
get that spot half just make sure I've got that so that's um a second okay so that's half
a distance between the bottom lip to that third I'm just going to check that again okay so it's
around there something like that okay then looking for a halfway point in this ear okay
show of the tragus so it's probably halfway so that it's called that antitragus
all right so somewhere around there okay so the bottom of the ear that comes to just one side
that tragus shape so it's one side of the tragus and that starts somewhere around there
got my apex here maybe that could be a bit higher could that be a bit higher
no that's all right things like that then you got that angle so you can look at this
you can use your brush okay so then you've got a change of angle there tragus
can look at that after okay so that's the ear it's in the back of the neck okay
it's going to come from here about there back of the neck
just looking for that angle for the back of the neck
okay and I'm going to look for the um okay I'm going to look for this little change of angle here
on the neck line so what does that line up with
just above the chin that's just above the chin line of the chin there that comes in like that
okay then where does this point come so it's almost in line with the eye so we can drop that down
somewhere around there okay and then it's slightly above then it's going to be slightly above
this line of the neck so
there's your neck just above hope for that angle should work out check it not quite
there on there not going to stress about it just around that get yourself can look for the
jawline so that point from there to there okay
actually we'll carry on with this right so we've got that that curve got our baseline in there
measure that curve okay now we can look for shall have a jaw and look for that change of
angle first another baseline change of angle where's that change of angle
just above the lip bottom of the lip okay something around that okay connect that to
looking for that angle and baseline okay look for the depth something parallel you can pull that in
the depth maybe a bit deeper okay so I'm going to look for the jawline okay so I've got these
one of us runs straight line there change of angle change of angle there
I'll go out change of angle comes up and the chin okay the jawline okay
maybe stick a look at this point to this point does that work out just use your brush
maybe just use the brush to find these angles
something around this angle something around that angle
so I'm just using my brush to approximate that line around there okay then we can start to look around
the tail end temple okay so I've got this shadow shape here comes up to about there okay
then look for this point here about studies in relation to the that's okay shape
it's most obvious reference point it's going to be somewhere around there okay
look for that angle next angle okay so actually kind of goes up a bit then comes back in
something like that and you've got this shape around the tragus
and shape just comes a bit above did like that then we're going to look across the um the fringe
okay so just looking across the fringe
these general changes of angle start with this apex about this is that just one side
so the I've got to put this halfway point that I
so it's just the one side is halfway point just on the inside of the pupil so yeah
just the one side there just a bit higher than that line here somewhere around there
okay change of angle change of angle kind of comes up that angle there comes back in itself
so there's another little step actually around there okay so that's the inner outline completed
now we can start to look at the features so look at the the apex of the brow okay
got that apex shape there comes down comes down to this point here okay so let's look for that
so where's that in relation to the halfway point of the eye just the one side
line above the the brow so it's going to be around here okay then you've got that next
change of direction just underneath the brow angle look at that distance from the plumb line
something around there okay then got this other angle inside here let's look for the lid
double that lid up it was just a bit higher than the brow line somewhere around there
okay so change direction just to one side that halfway mark change direction
that side put the thickness of the pupil in just slightly wider than that
indication of the pupil in the width the iris okay so that line kind of comes all the way down here
like so comes across there so it's almost in line with the pupil
the iris sorry okay just on the inside that change of angle
the eyelid this change of angle just one side
the iris there change of angle it's up there gonna come straight it turns up
let's go for the eye shape this side the eye shape on the other side now okay so we've got the um
let's put this in here this line here is guideline okay
angle the underside of the eyelid line there okay the lid more or less hits that line
all right so that's what's that that's about halfway got that halfway
just remember which side the smallest level it's head lower it's about there
okay let's measure that and that comes in change of angle there for the lid okay I'll just put this
nose in for a context so the change of angle for the nose unless it happens where that lid
shape is there and just gonna check out some of that thickness that line there okay iris
it's gonna come it's about there with a V shape okay kind of follows that line the iris the um
eyelid from the eyelid turns like that okay then the brow comes up there slight change of angle
so the nose okay just make these shapes a bit bigger you can see what's going on okay
so look at this change of angle for the nose it's just one side of the plum line okay so
I'm going from that thickness of the line there there's your change of angle
nose kind of ends on that shape there okay so where does the nose start in relation to the
tear duct that's your tear duct it's going to start down there okay so the shadow comes just above the
line the shadow here it's the plum line so it's just above the shadow it's the plum line
change of direction okay then got this kind of change of direction
just the one side of the plum line with this V shape here that comes down
back up to the nose there okay then if you look at the lips okay it's got a slight change of
angle corner to corner okay do that top lip the top and bottom lip there middle lip separation
okay so keep his bow it's that plum line okay angle of the bottom of the lip it's the plum line
corner of the mouth in line with that center point okay look straight kind of straightens off
got this thickness that kind of comes up like so and we've got this scent here that comes up
oops the lip okay that hits the plum line shape there okay so I've got the um
so I'm just looking for this point here the plum line something about there that kind of comes out
around there one of the lip is out there and you've got the inner side of the lip okay so
just finish off this eye shadow shape you actually it's a bit of a shadow shape here
look for that point down to this point
like a straight line change of angle change of angling up okay so that's kind of in line
the two dot okay that angle triangle next angle okay so I'm gonna look at the hair okay we'll look at
the um that bum shape at the back first like so we need to look at the ear just look at the ear
okay so we're gonna look for the this angle we've already got that angle
tragus anti tragus just putting that in there okay look at this change of angle here
to get the thickness of the helix that kind of angle there that kind of comes up on itself okay
then across the helix so it turns into a conch anti helix sorry it turns into a conch
it's like an ecoms like that then just gonna line these shapes up then it's like your anti helix
an angle there something in the middle with an accent underneath the tragus I kind of
put it in there it's an articulation okay look at this curve shape up here
so the bun right it's gonna look this shape here now so it comes down there okay then as
an overall shape that comes up there so I'm just gonna guess this it's just gonna drops down
here comes up there it's back down okay moving over next
what we change of angle it's back down okay then this change of angle in the middle okay
you got this little shape there okay there's a bit of a bump in there it comes up a bit higher
okay so then
articulations got this little articulation here
the one there don't have the hairline then round here there's a bit of a something there
okay then look at this rest of this hairline okay so here just run that profile it kind of comes
up a bit there change direction so then following this line here a bit of a curve oops missed all that
so it's saying you can look at some of these articulations
round here so these little articulations coming off it mean towards this little shape here
and that one kind of comes round it's that point okay that kind of comes up there articulation in there
right simple the rest of here I'm just going to group all this this shape in here so I'm just
going to group all that one tone so just blend that angle there just think about that shape
and it comes back down just look at these hair shapes okay so the actual
sort of there's round there this is transitioned okay so that's roughly um yellow shapes okay so
I'm going to start to fill things in okay a bit of line weight okay in around the lip
okay side shape clinging the shadows okay look at the rest of the
rest of the head that chin and neck the sharper edge softer edge so I'm going to fill all this
just bring all this stuff in around the neck or not all of it just some of it okay
just around the hair okay got this curl shape in there just using the flat side of my brush
get a sense of that curl it's all there okay got the ear okay okay just looking in the ear
look at these shapes in the hair okay okay so that's the um okay that's the
shadow shapes complete okay that's it shadow shapes that's from this in
background okay so that's the finish
shadows shadow shapes done